Let's go back to the problem.
では 問題に 戻りましょう
We want to track a pedestrian moving in front of our autonomous vehicle.
自動運転車の 前方を 歩く 歩行者を 追跡します
At its core, the Kalman filter is a two-step estimation problem,
本質的には、カルマンフィルターには 2ステップの推定問題、
predict and then update.
つまり予測と更新があります
We always start with what we already know from the past about the pedestrian.
最初にあるのは 歩行者について わかっている 過去の情報です
We use that information to predict the state of the pedestrian up to the time
それを 使って 次の測定値が 届くまでの 歩行者の状態を
when the next measurement arrives, and this is called the prediction step.
予測します これが 予測段階です
The next step is called the update step, where we essentially use the new
更新段階と 呼ばれる 次の段階で 新しい観測値を 使い
observations to correct our belief about the state of the pedestrian.
歩行者の状態に関する 予測を 修正します
The Kalman filter simply consists of an endless loop of prediction/update steps,
カルマンフィルターは 予測と更新の 無限ループから 成り立つだけで
this is what you built with Sebastian earlier in this module.
これは このモジュールの冒頭で Sebastianと 一緒に 作成したものです
But what happens when there are two sensors that observe the same
では 2つのセンサーが 同じ歩行者を 観測した場合は
pedestrian?
どうなるでしょうか
How does that change the Kalman comma filter?
カルマンフィルターは どう変わるでしょうか
Actually, we can keep the same processing flow with the difference that
その場合も 同じプロセスフローが 使えますが それぞれのセンサーが 独自の
each sensor is going to have its own prediction/update scheme.
予測・更新スキームを 使用することに なります
In other words, the belief about the pedestrian's position and
言い換えると 歩行者の位置や 速度に 関する 予測は
velocity is updated asynchronously
新しい観測値が 届くたびに
each time new measurement is received regardless the source sensor.
それがどのセンサーの ものかとは無関係に 非同期更新されます
Let's step through an example flow to see how it works.
では サンプルフローを 実行して 仕組みを 見てみましょう
Here the pedestrian state at time k is a distribution with
ここで 時点kに おける 歩行者の状態の 分布は
its mean (x) and covariance (P).
平均をX 共分散をP とします
Let's say we're now at time k + 1, and
時点k+1に 達したとき
we've just received the laser measurement.
レーザー測定値が 届いたとしましょう
The first thing we do before we look at the measurement update
新しい測定値を 見る前に 行うことは
is to make a prediction about where we
歩行者が 時点kから 時点k+1 までの
think the pedestrian from time k will be at time k+1.
間に どこまで進むかを 予測することです
The second thing we do is the so called measurement update, where we
その後 測定値を更新し 予測された歩行者の状態に
combine the pedestrian's predicted state with the new laser measurement.
新しいレーザー測定値を 組み合わせます
What we now have is a more accurate belief about the pedestrian's position
これによって 時点k+1に おける 歩行者の予測位置が もっと
at time k+1, this is what we call the posterior.
正確になります これを 事後確率と いいます
Now let's imagine that we receive the radar measurement at time k+2.
今度は 時点k+2で レーダー測定値が 届いたとしましょう
First, we again predict the pedestrian state from k+1 to k+2.
この場合も まずは 時点k+1から 時点k+2までの 歩行者の状態を 予測します
Note, this prediction for
レーダーの場合も
radar is exactly the same function as in the laser case.
予測方法は レーザーの場合と まったく同じです
What changes, in this case, is the Measurement Update step.
違うのは 測定値の更新段階です
As we know, the radar sees the word differently than laser.
ご存知のとおり レーダーと レーザーでは 物の 見方が違います
While laser provides measurement in a Cartesian coordinate system,
レーザーの 測定値は デカルト座標系で 表現され
radar provides measurement in a polar coordinate system.
レーダーの測定値は 極座標系で 表現されます
Thus we have to use different measurement update functions specific
そのため レーダーデータには 異なる 測定値更新関数を 使う
to radar data, so this is a more detailed view of the Kalman filter.
必要があります これがカルマンフィルターの 詳細です
We received the measurements from different sensors at each timestamp, and
各時点で 異なるセンサーから 測定値を 受け取って 予測を行い
then we make a prediction followed by a measurement update.
それに続いて 測定値の更新を 行います
Are you following me so far?
ここまで いいですか?
In the next quiz, I want you to continue this flow, but
次のクイズでは 自分で このフローを 進めてください
this time let's think about predicting and updating if data from
ただし 今度は 時点k+3で 異なるセンサーからの データが
different sensors arrive simultaneously at time k+3
同時に 届いた場合の 予測と更新について 考えます